Guide to the Adolph Sutro Papers, 1861-1899 JL004
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Adolph Sutro Papers,
1861-1899
JL004
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
1.0 Linear feet
General note
NOTE: The correspondence on the Sutro Tunnel contains letters written by Pelham Ames and R.S. Raw; many of these are directed to one another rather than to Sutro himself. Both men were secretaries to Adolph Sutro. With very few exceptions, all other correspondence is addressed to Sutro himself.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection of his papers includes correspondence dealing with the construction of the Sutro Tunnel (1869-1896; with a possible date of 1867); applications for employment on the tunnel project (1873-1877) and in the Baths (1892-1895); personal bills (1869-1890); miscellaneous correspondence (1870-1895); miscellaneous papers and printed matter (1865-1889); and a safe book (1861-1899).
The correspondence dealing with the Sutro Tunnel is arranged in alphabetical order by author; with few exceptions all correspondence is addressed to Sutro. The number in parenthesis following each name indicates the number of letters written by that correspondent; when only one piece of correspondence is included, there is no such indication. The miscellaneous correspondence is also listed alphabetically, with each letter listed with date and a brief subject identification. A letter of particular interest in this group is one written by Cyrus Adler of the Smithsonian Institution; Adler was a Jewish scholar, educator and author, and wrote to Sutro in 1890 regarding a manuscript that Sutro possessed in his library. Certain personal letters, such as correspondence to Sutro from the schools that his children attended, are also included.
The large percentage of material pertaining to the Sutro Tunnel makes this collection of his papers particularly valuable to anyone interested in that important achievement; in addition, certain aspects of his character and personality are given some light through the varied miscellaneous correspondence.
BIOGRAPHY
Adolph Heinrich Sutro was born in Prussia in 1830. He came to the United States in 1850, to California in 1851, and to Nevada in 1860. Sutro was the mining engineer who planned the Sutro Tunnel, which was constructed through Mount Davidson to reach the Comstock lode. The tunnel was built between 1869 and 1878 and cost $6,500,00 to build. In 1878 Sutro sold his interest in the tunnel and invested in San Francisco real estate, most notably the Cliff House and the Sutro Baths. He was elected mayor of San Francisco in 1894 for one term, and died in 1898.
Provenance:
Gift of the Sutro family, date unknown
Access Restrictions:
None.
- Miscellaneous correspondence (arranged alphabetically) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cyrus Adler- of the Smithsonian Institution, re: MS is Sutro's library, 1890
  - P.W. Amez- telegram copy, advice, 1877
  - D.R. Ashley- suit against McCall, 1870
  - Astronomical Society of the Pacific- from Chas. Burckhalter, Sec'y, notice of Sutro's election to the Society, 1890
  - Mary P. Banks- re: her son, 1872
  - G. Behrend- in German, 1887 Oct. 19 and Oct. 23
  - J.D. Bethel- personal requests, Sept 30, 1877 and Dec 2. 1879
  - F. Brandis & Co.- price of instruments, 1877
  - Murray Brothers- machine estimates, 1887
  - Daniel S. Brown- death of Dr. Reninger, 1877
  - California Electric Light Co.- answer, 1887
  - W.C. Chapin- pipe measurements and prices, 1890
  - E.B. Church- explanation of bill, 1876
  - J.A. Church- reply to invitation, 1877
  - Ellwood Cooper- letter of introduction, 1889
  - Easton, Eldridge & Co.- San Francisco real estate, 1889
  - Eisen & Stewart- (Gustav Eisen)- personal, 1887
  - Geographical Society of the Pacific- from C.M. Grant, notice of Sutro's election to the Society-, 1890
  - A. Goldsmith- information - - telegram, inquiry, Sept 9, 1877; Sept 16, 1877
  - J. Habets- in German, 1887
  - Catherine H. Hittell- Central Pacific RR. government ownership, 1895
  - Holladay & Holladay- Calif. School of Mechanical Arts, 1890 Jan 21 and Jan 25
  - George Houston- stable bill, 1887
  - J.W. Howland- electricity experiments, 1877
  - H. Hunt- Bordeaux wines, 1877
  - A. J. Hutchinson- wood order, 1877
  - F.C. Innes & Co.- Vancouver real estate, 1886
  - David Johnson- re: Edgar Sutro at school (son), (St. Matthew's Hall, San Mateo), and, 1877 Oct. 11 and Nov. 9 1877 Nov. 10
  - G.W. Johnson- real estate, (2), Oct 19, 1887
  - R.F. Kelker- death of Dr. Renninger, 1877
  - A. Kemble- rare books collection offer, 1886
  - C.R. Kerger- in German, 1890
  - F. Von Leicht- transit instrument, sale, 1887
  - Max Levy- subscription list to San Francisco Cremation Co., 1890 Jan 22 and Jan 26
  - A. Lincoln- magnesium lamps, 1872
  - J. Livingston- request for deed, 1877
  - Lyle- pedigree of Matt Gunn, Sutro's horse, 1877
  - W.H. Martin- Olympic Club baseball park, 1887
  - H.P. Merritt- mules, 1877
  - Mrs. E.F. Mills- re: Rosa, 1877
  - L.L. Mills- re: Rosa, daughter, (2 letters), 1887 Nov
  - Mrs. J.H. Mills- character of certain officials, 1877 Mar. 3-4
  - William Mooney- telegram for money, 1877
  - J.G. Negley- invention to Patent Office, 1877
  - J. Palamountain- stereoscope, 1877
  - Henry Pennington- letters re: his disappearance
    - 1. notes
    - 2. I.O. Acton, 1895
    - 3. Taylor Rogers, Nov 22, 1895
    - 4. Taylor Rogers, Nov 23, 1895
    - 5. I.O. Acton, 1896
    - 6. Taylor Rogers, 1896
  - F.P. Perkins- re: literary work, 1886
  - J.B. Pitchford- estimates on machinery, 1877 and 1887
  - Lewis R. Price- personal note, 1876
  - J.H. Raymond- (Vassar College), in re: to Sutro's daughter, 1877
  - J.W. Reid- regret at not seeing Sutro, 1890
  - G.A. Rerch, M.D.- in German, 1877
  - Miss M. Reinhardt- pamphlet on the English & German Boarding and Day School, 1873
  - R. Rickord- inquiry re: air compressing and drilling machinery, 1877
  - William H. Rideing- elections, 1877
  - G. Specht- in German -, 1877 July and 1877 Oct.
  - C.D. Turk- telegram re: team of horses, 1877
  - Robert Warner- notice of receipt of letter, 1887
  - Henry A. Wasmuth- in German, 1887
  - George H. Watson- request that Kate, Sutro's daughter be allowed to remain at Laurel Hall, 1877
  - Mrs. G.H. Watson- instructions re- Kate's departure from Laurel Hall, 1877
  - H. Werderman- instructions, 1877
  - E.J. Wickson- info. on olives, 1889
  - Wimmer & Co.- portrait of Sutro, 1890
  - John B. Winters- -Water Commission, 1877
  - George Woods & Co.- condensing process for dryrooms, 1877
  - W.L. Woods- regret, 1877
  - O.F. von Rhein & Co.- Golden Gate and Webster St. lots, 1890
- Correspondence: George W. Merritt, reports to Sutro on real estate, taxes, conditions of his property., 1889 Feb 22-July 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Personal bills - insurance, children's school bills, accommodations, clothing, etc. (chronological arrangement), 1869-August 1877 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Personal bills, Sept 1877-1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Applications for employment: Sutro baths (chronological arrangement), 1892-1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Applications for employment: Sutro Tunnel (chronological arrangement), 1873-1877 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence re: Sutro Tunnel: Adamson to Billmeyer (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - W.R. Adamson, agent, 1887
  - Joseph Aird price list, 1873
  - Alta Boiler Works, 1872
  - Pelham W. Ames (19), Jan-March 1877
  - John Anderson, 1872
  - W.G. Armstrong & Co. (2) diagrams (2), Sept-Oct 1873
  - Artesian Well Boring Tools- price list
  - Atkins Brothers, 1875
  - William Augerman, April-May 1877
  - W.W. Bailey, 1877
  - L.N. Baker, 1877
  - Bandmann, Nielsen & Co. (2) form letter, June, Dec 1875
  - Chas. Beer (12), Oct-Dec 1873
  - J.L. Bell (4), April-May 1876
  - Porter Bell & Co., 1872
  - William B. Bement, 1872
  - F.A. Benjamin (8), Nov 1873-Feb 1874
  - William Berry, 1877
  - E. Biddle (2), May, Dec 1877
  - Bigelow & Johnston, 1872
  - Billmeyer & Smalls, 1876
- Correspondence re: Sutro Tunnel: Bishop to Brown (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Victor Bishop & Co., 1877
  - H.C. Blanchard, 1872
  - William Bohn, 1877
  - M.J. Bolan, 1877
  - D.J. Bousfield, 1877
  - B.L. Brandt, 1873
  - Henry L. Brevoort (3), June-August 1872
  - Lyman Bridges & Co. (8), March-Dec 1877
  - B.F. Brown, 1878
  - Thomas Brown (proprietor of The Burleigh Rock Drill) (62), Oct 1873-March 1879
- Correspondence re: Sutro Tunnel: Bounton to Burleigh (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - J.D. [Bounton?), 1874
  - C.H. Bryan, 1877
  - Burleigh Rock Drill Co. (39), July 1870-Dec 1876
- Correspondence re: Sutro Tunnel: California Powder Works to Kruse & Euler (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - California Powder Works, 1875
  - A.S. Cameron & Co., 1872
  - W.H. Cameron (Edinburgh & District Water Trust) (2), June, July 1873
  - Campbell, 1869
  - Carroll & Snyder, 1872
  - Lewis Chalmers, 1877
  - Chaudoir, 1873
  - Michael Chevalier, 1877
  - A.R. Chisholm, 1877
  - Arthur Chomaly, 1877
  - G.M. Clements (2), Jan 1877
  - Cochrane, Grove & Co., 1873
  - L.W. Conn, 1877
  - Co-operative Iron & Steel Works, 1876
  - Cope & Maxwell Manufacturing Co., 1876
  - Craven Bros., 1874
  - Capt. C.B. Dahlgren, 1877
  - Dana & Co., (2), May, July 1872
  - Charles S. Davis, 1876
  - E.S. Davis, 1877
  - Davis & Riker, 1872
  - James Delavan, 1877
  - Diamond Rock Boring Co., 1873
  - H.L. Dinker, 1877
  - W. & B. Douglas, 1877
  - George Driver, 1877
  - Dubois & Francois (3), 1873
  - D.W. Earl, 1872
  - A. Eilers, 1877
  - Robert Fairlie (2), Nov 1873
  - Federated Trades and Labor Organization, 1887
  - J.N. Flint, 1877
  - William B. Frue (2), 1877
  - Edward Greene, 1877
  - H.B. Hanmore (6), Feb-April 1877
  - Dennis Harrington, 1877
  - C.N. Harris Dec (2), 1877
  - A.0. Harrison, 1890
  - Harrison Boiler Works - Price list, 1872
  - George L. Harvey, 1877
  - Harvey & Co., 1873
  - Haskins Machine Co., 1872
  - J.E. Hilgard, 1877
  - Charles L. Hoffmann, 1876
  - Henry Howard & Co. Iron gas tube and fitting list, 1873; 1872
  - Dr. J.W. Howland, 1877
  - Joseph Hyman, 1877
  - The Ingersoll Rock Drill Co. (3), 1874-1877
  - W.H. Jewell, 1875
  - Owen Kelly, 1877
  - Kelton & Thomas, 1877
  - M.A. Kelton, 1877
  - Kimball Manufacturing Co., 1872
  - Carl Kley Oct-Nov (3), 1873
  - John Knowles Fitting list, 1873; 1871
  - Knowles Patent Steam Pump Works, 1872
  - Kruse & Euler, 1875
- Correspondence re: Sutro Tunnel: Lance to Office of Public Printer (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - George F. Lance, 1876
  - Land Department, 1877
  - [W.C.?] Lewis, [1867?]
  - Lloyd & Lloyd (6); Iron gas tube and fitting list, 1873
  - J.P. Loya, 1877
  - George G. Lyon (4), 1872
  - J.W. Macdermott, 1873
  - Robert Maclaren, 1873
  - Charles G. Mann, 1877
  - P. Marcelin, 1876
  - Maschinenbau-Actien-Gesellschaft HUMBOLDT - vormals Sievers & Comp. (4), 1873
  - [P. Mauris?], 1875
  - J.W. Maxwell 18 77
  - F.B. Mercer (10), 1876-1877
  - J.H.P. Merigold, 1877
  - H.P. Merritt, 1877
  - Milburn & Co. Ltd. Circular, 1873
  - J.G. Mitchell, 1872
  - E.J. Moore, 1887
  - J.C. Mormsey, 1873
  - Henry G. Morris, 1872
  - Morris, Tasker & Co. (6), 1872-1873
  - George M. Mowbray, 1877
  - Francis Murphy, 1877
  - Thomas McCloskey, 1877
  - J. McCone, 1872
  - Thomas McGill & Co., 1877
  - Thomas H. McGrath, 1877
  - McKean & Co., 1876
  - William McLeod, 1877
  - Narrow Gauge RR Construction & Supply Co., 1872
  - John [Newton?], 1872
  - Thad [Norris?), 1872
  - J.H. Nottage, 1874
  - Parke & Lacy (3), 1876-1877
  - Pennsylvania Diamond Drill Co., 1872
  - Philadelphia & Reading RR Co. (2), 1873, 1876
  - T.E. Picotte (2), Oct, Nov 1876
  - W.S. Pinney, 1872
  - Henry Pleasants (13), 1872-1873
  - Porter, Bell & Co., 1873
  - Lewis R. Price, 1877
  - Public Printer, Office of, 1877
- Correspondence re: Sutro Tunnel: Raggi to John Russell & Co. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bernardo Raggi, 1889
  - A.C. Rand, 1872
  - R.S. Raw (22), 1876-1877
  - Henry Reid, 1874
  - Garrett Reilly, 1877
  - George Reuling, M.D., 1877
  - J.B. Reynolds (see also Ingersoll Rock Drill) (4), 1876-1877
  - W.H. Rideing, 1877
  - R.S. Ripley, 1873
  - E.A.L. Roberts, 1876
  - I.B. Robertson, 1877
  - Wilhelm Rose (2), 1877
  - Ross & Co., 1877
  - Root Steam Engine Co., 1872
  - P.R. and F.M. Roots Circular on rotary blowers, 1872; 1869
  - Royal Mail Steam Packet Co., [1874?]
  - Charles Rulison, 1877
  - John Russell & Co., 1873
- Correspondence re: Sutro Tunnel: Safford to Young (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - H.S. Safford, 1873
  - Schmeisser, Wench & Co., 1874
  - Seligman, 1877
  - F. Shanly (3), 1872-1873
  - Shellabarger & Wilson (8), 1875-1877
  - Shotts Iron Works, 1873
  - James R. Smedberg, 1879
  - Emma G. Smith, 1877
  - H. Smith Jr., 1875
  - H.G. Smith & Co., 1872
  - George W. Snyder, 1872-1873
  - C.H. Stegman, l877
  - J.H. Struckdinger, 1877
  - [W?] Stursberg, 1877
  - Sutro & Co., l879
  - G.C. Thaxter, 1877
  - B.B. Thayer, 1877
  - William Thorpe, 1877
  - Tipton & Pollock, 1877
  - S.S. Townsend (3), 1872
  - Virginia and Truckee RR Co. (2), 1877
  - Union and Central Pacific RR Line (2), 1872
  - H. Hussey Vivian, 1877
  - O.F. von Rhein & Co., 1890
  - Waring & Parke, Engineers, 1872
  - R.W. Warren (Vulcan Powder Works), 1877
  - Franz Welter, 1873
  - J.W. Willard, 1875
  - Hon. J.A. Williamson (4), 1877
  - [Wilson, McLay & Co.?], 1873
  - James Woods, 1877
  - W.L. Woods (2 letters, one re bill in the House of Representatives), 1877
  - Wright & Sanders, Architects, 1886
  - Frank S. Young (4), 1877
- Miscellaneous papers re: Sutro Tunnel (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Notes, [1877?]
  - Memoranda
  - Summaries
  - Statements
  - Unidentified material
- Adolph Sutro: Safe book, 1861-1899 (Box 2, Folder 15)